RAHUL TEVATIA

Cell: +1 (682) 283-6675 Email: rahul.tevatia@mavs.uta.edu LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/rahul-tevatia-93660530/ Github: github.com/rtevatia4

Professional Summary

Enthusiastic achiever with strong computer science background, project experiences and strong skillset applicable across financial, IT and other sectors. Possess programming skills with over **4.5 years of professional IT experience** in software engineering, product development, DevOps automation, system implementation and design. I am currently pursuing Master's in Computer Science to enhance my skills and experiences.

Core Competencies and Skills

Programming & Scripting Languages: Python (proficient), Java (Intermediate), C (proficient), COBOL (Intermediate), PL/SQL, JavaScript, HTML+CSS, XML, Shell Scripting (Batch).

Databases & Business Tools: Oracle Database, MySQL, IBM DB2 Subsystem, Eclipse, PyCharm, SQL Server Management Studio, Visual Studio, JIRA, Github, MS Visio, MS Excel, SSIS/ETL.

Operating Systems: UNIX, Mainframe Z/OS, Linux, Windows NT.

Other Skills: Data Integration (SSIS) & ETL, Data Modelling, System Infrastructure architecting and Design.

Education

The University of Texas at Arlington.

Master of Science in Computer Science, Specialization in AI and Data.

Arlington, Texas, USA.

Aug 2019 - Anticipated 2021

GPA: 3.5

Dr. APJ Abdul Kalam Technical University (Formerly UPTU).

Bachelor of Technology – Computer Science & Engineering.

Gr. Noida, NCR, India. Aug 2010 - June 2014

GPA: 3.5

Relevant Coursework: Algorithms and Data Structures, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Database Systems, Software Engineering, Data Analysis and Modelling Techniques.

Professional Experience

Takaud Savings and Pensions B.S.C. (c)

Manama, Kingdom of Bahrain Sep 2017 - July 2019

Developer

- Reduced **manual overhead** of operations and customer experience team by developing an application that provides the summarized daily transactions details of requested customers.
- Responsible for various developments, enhancements of the business solutions using **Python**, **Java**, **SQL**, **Shell Scripting and Data**, majorly built many applications to support business functions and operations.

Cognizant Technology Solutions

Jr. Product Specialist

Kolkata, India

July 2014 - Aug 2017

- Migrated the many COBOL modules responsible for financial transactions to Java based frameworks.
- Increased the Oracle database and DB2 subsystem performance by 30% faster by optimizing the SQL queries.

Relevant Projects

OmniSearchAPP - Built the Takaud Client and Transaction Details lookup GUI utility using **Python** to fetch requested client details and provides the summarized transaction activities. Used **tkinter**, **Pandas**, **pyodbc**, openpyxl python libraries to build GUI, to interact, to get data from database and to present or format the data.

Issue Tracking Register - Completed during Industrial Training at UTI Infrastructure Technology and Services LTD., Delhi. Outlined, Developed and completed a web based Issue Tracking register to track bugs and issues experienced within an organization.

Criminal Identification System - This was a web based project which aimed to help and support the investigative agencies in crime scene investigation and forensics. Used HTML, CSS, Java, JSP, Servlet, Java Script, MySQL.

Achievements and extra-curricular

- Received various organizational awards like "Pat on the Back", "Star Rookie of the Month" at Cognizant.
- "Project of the Year Clustered" Award in 2015 by TIAA, USA through Cognizant.
- Published a research paper at International Conference on Electrical, Electronics and Computer Science on, "E-Banking-A Revolution in banking sector Virtual Bank" Paper Id: ICEEECS-02024-232, Feb 2014, India.